Finding aid to the Laurie Worcester papers CA.MS.00069
Smith College Archives
Laurie Worcester papers
1943-1995
Smith College Archives
Worcester, Laurie (Lucy Lawrence Chauncey).
CA.MS.00069
2.083 linear feet (5 containers)
Smith graduate. Contains articles, photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and lecture notes.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the Laurie Worcester collection were given to the College Archives in 1978 by her husband, Henry Chauncey.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biography
II. Personal Correspondence
III. Lecture Notes.
Biographical / Historical
Lucy Lawrence "Laurie" Worcester came to Smith in 1948. She had previously attended the Brearly School, a prestigious girls school in Manhattan. She was elected president of Student Council and served as class president from 1952-1957. She wrote and edited the Tenth Reunion Yearbook. Laurie was elected director of the Alumnae Association, and served on a committee formed to revise sections of the association's bylaws as well as the editorial board of the Smith Alumnae Quarterly.
After graduating from Smith, Laurie was on the editorial staff of Time, Inc., and later taught history at Miss Fine's School in Princeton. In 1954 she married Henry Chauncey, president of Educational Testing Service. They had four daughters: Susan, Caroline, Deborah, and Sarah.
From 1955-1970, Laurie and Henry Chauncy lived in an 18th century farmhouse on Rosedale Road in Princeton, New Jersey. The house was later converted into a Guest House and became part of the Henry Chauncey Conference Center in 1973. On May 3, 1976, the house was renamed Laurie House in honor of Laurie Worcester Chauncy.
Related Material
80. Class of 1952 Records
80. Student Council - Photographs
90. Alumnae Trust Nominees 1965
Scope and Contents
The Laurie Worcester papers consist of approximately two and one half linear feet. The collection includes such biographical material as articles, photographs, and newspaper clippings. The bulk of the collection consists of a series of letters Laurie wrote to her family during her years at Smith, as well as notebooks and exams from her time at Smith. The collection of letters consists of 167 documents written between the years 1948-1952. These include 92 letters, 59 postcards, 9 telegrams, 6 newspaper clippings, and 1 commencement publication. A description of the content of these letters, written by Henry Chauncey, is included in the Series Description. In addition to the letters from Laurie, there is a bound book of letters received after her death.
The class notebooks span four years and represent a diverse selection of classes, including: Art, Art History, Ancient Drama, English, French, Geology, Government, History, Historiography, Religion, and Sociology. The notebooks are organized by subject matter and then by date. In addition, there is a collection of notes from Laurie's time at Brearly School, prior to her matriculation at Smith.
The Smith College Archives houses other items related to Laurie Worcester that are not kept among the Laurie Worcester Papers. Laurie Worcester is in a photograph taken with members of the Student Council, located in that file. In addition, reference to Lauire can be found in Alumnae Trust Nominees for 1965.
The following is an introduction to the collection written by Laurie Worcester's husband, Henry Chauncy:
"Laurie wrote home quite regularly throughout her four years at Smith-certainly more than most students then or now. The letters, being to her family, report very personally and in considerable detail on what she had been doing and what lay ahead. They provide a picture of an active person of wide-ranging interests who had an extremely full and rewarding college life. The letters give a picture of what college was like in the post-World War II period and they give some insight into a remarkable person. Laurie was energetic and enthusiastic, interested in other people, with a lively sense of humor and a quick wit. She was greatly concerned with the life of the College in all its aspects: academic, extracurricular, and even athletic-though no star. She used to comment that she was the last person to make the lacrosse team at the very end of her senior year.
In other areas she was more successful. She was elected to Phi Beta Kappa in her junior year and was President of the Student Council in her senior year.
Fortunately, Laurie's mother kept her letters-in a large box which I was given after her death. Since in most cases the letters were not in their original envelopes and were not in any order, and since Laurie ordinarily dated her letters only by the day of the week, it has been difficult to arrange them in chronological order. Some letters, on closer scrutiny, may be found out of place. Order, in any case, does not seem to be of highest importance. Each letter speaks for itself and gives a vignette of like at Smith and a snapshot of the author."
The collection consists of 167 documents written between the years 1948-1952. These include 92 letters, 59 postcards, 9 telegrams, 6 newspaper clippings, and 1 commencement publication. Because many of the letters were dated only by the day of the week, each piece has been reviewed carefully for evidence of chronology. The use of the perpetual calendar has helped place the collection in chronological order. However, the researcher must be aware that the order is not definitive.
"Letters from Smith" are arranged in 12 folders. Each folder contains documents for a three-month period. Correspondence from Laurie's freshman year are in folders 1-3, her sophomore year in folders 4-6, her junior year in folders 7-9, and her senior year in folders 10-12. A newspaper clipping from the fall of 1952, featuring Laurie's return to Smith College, will be found in folder 12."
Worcester, Laurie.; Smith College--Students.; Brearley School--Students.
- Series I. Biography
  - General, 1947-1995 (Box 2183, Folder 1)
  - General, undated (Box 2183, Folder 2)
- Series II. Personal Correspondence
  - "Letters from Smith" inventory (Box 2183, Folder 3)
  - Letters freshman year, 1948; Sept. - Dec. (Box 2183, Folder 4)
  - Letters freshman year, 1949; Jan. - Mar. (Box 2183, Folder 5)
  - Letters freshman year, 1949; Apr. - Jun. (Box 2183, Folder 6)
  - Letters sophomore year, 1949; Sept. - Dec. (Box 2183, Folder 7)
  - Letters sophomore year, 1950; Jan. - Mar. (Box 2183, Folder 8)
  - Letters sophomore year, 1950; Apr. - May (Box 2183, Folder 9)
  - Letters junior year, 1950; Sept. - Dec. (Box 2183, Folder 10)
  - Letters junior year, 1951; Jan. - Mar. (Box 2183, Folder 11)
  - Letters junior year, 1951; Apr. - Jun. (Box 2183, Folder 12)
  - Letters senior year, 1951; Sept. - Dec. (Box 2183, Folder 13)
  - Letters senior year, 1952; Jan. - Mar. (Box 2183, Folder 14)
  - Letters senior year, 1952; Apr. - Jun; Sept. (Box 2183, Folder 15)
- Series III. Lecture Notes
  - Lecture Notes - Art 11 (1), 1949-1950 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Art 11 (2), 1949-1950 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Art History (1), 1949-1950 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Art History (2), 1949-1950 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Brearly School (1), 1943-1948 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Brearly School (2), 1943-1948 (Box 2184)
  - Lecture Notes - Brearly School (3), 1943-1948 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - Ancient Drama, 1950-1951 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - English 21, 1948-1949 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - English 39b, 4176, 1949-1952 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - French, 1948-1949 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - Geology, 1949-1950 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - Government, 1951-1952 (Box 2185)
  - Lecture Notes - History 11 (1), 1948-1949 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - History 11 (2), 1948-1949 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - Hist. Ancnt Nr Estrn Hist., 1949-1950 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - History 411b, 1950-1951 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - History French Revolution, 1951 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - History 322a, 38b, 1951-1952 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - History 45a, 46b, 1951-1952 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - Hist. Tudor Stewart Ren., 1950-1951 (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - Hist. Medieval History, undated (Box 2186)
  - Lecture Notes - Historiography, 1950-1951 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Historiography Comp. Exam, 1950-1951 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Maps, undated (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Religion 11, 1949-1950 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Religion 32b, 1949-1950 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Sociology (1), 1949-1950 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Sociology (2), 1949-1950 (Box 2187)
  - Lecture Notes - Outlines for Comprehensives, 1951 (Box 2187)